<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Kategorie: Zitate | Ne cede malis]]></title>
  <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/categories/zitate/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-31T13:26:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://necedemalis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Frasier Crane]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[admin@necedemalis.info]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Machtkonzentration und Machtteilung]]></title>
    <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/06/10/machtkonzentration-und-machtteilung/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-10T14:44:30+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/06/10/machtkonzentration-und-machtteilung</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>"</em>[...]<em> many liberal socialists are guided in their endeavors by the tragic illusion that by depriving private individuals of the power they possess in an individualist system, and by transferring this power to society, they can thereby extinguish power. What all those who argue in this manner overlook is that, <a href="http://europa.eu/lisbon_treaty/glance/index_de.htm">by concentrating power</a> so that it can be used in the service of a single plan, it is not merely transferred but infinitely heightened; that, by uniting in the hands of some single body power formerly exercised independently by many, an amount of power is created infinitely greater than any that existed before, so much more far-reaching as almost to be different in kind. It is entirely fallacious when it is sometimes argued that the great power exercised by a central planning board would be 'no greater than the power collectively exercised by private boards of directors.' There is, in a competitive society, nobody who can exercise even a fraction of the power which a socialist planning board would possess, and if nobody can consciously use the power, it is just an abuse of words to assert that it rests with all the capitalists put together. It is merely a play upon words to speak of the 'power collectively exercised by private boards of directors' so long as they do not combine to concerted action – which would, of course, mean the end of competition and the creation of a planned economy. <strong>To split or decentralize power is necessarily to reduce the absolute amount of power, and the competitive system is the only system designed to minimize by decentralization the power exercised by man over man. </strong>
We have seen before how the separation of economic and political aims is an essential guaranty of individual freedom and how it is consequently attacked by all collectivists. To this we must now add that the 'substitution of political for economic power' now <a href="https://derstandard.at/1332324022080/Nationalrat---Oberhauser-Der-ungeregelte-Finanzmarkt-ist-schuld-ander-Krise-nicht-die-Oesterreicherinnen-und-Oesterreicher">so often demanded</a> means necessarily the substitution of power from which there is no escape for a power which is always limited. What is called economic power, while it can be an instrument of coercion, is, in the hands of private individuals, never exclusive or complete power, never power over the whole life of a person. <strong>But centralized as an instrument of political power it creates a degree of dependence scarcely distinguishable from slavery.</strong>"</em></p>

<p>[Friedrich A. von Hayek – The Road to Serfdom (1944), 144f.]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Essenz des Individualismus]]></title>
    <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/06/03/essenz-des-individualismus/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-03T04:09:46+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/06/03/essenz-des-individualismus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>"This is the fundamental fact on which the whole philosophy of individualism is based. It does not assume, as is often asserted, that man is egoistic or selfish or ought to be. It merely starts from the indisputable fact that the limits of our powers of imagination make it impossible to include in our scale of values more than a sector of the needs of the whole society, and that, since, strictly speaking, scales of value can exist only in individual minds, nothing but partial scales of values exist—scales which are inevitably different and often inconsistent with each other. From this the individualist concludes that the individuals should be allowed, within defined limits, to follow their own values and preferences rather than somebody else's; <strong>that within these spheres the individual's system of ends should be supreme and not subject to any dictation by others</strong>. It is this recognition of the individual as the ultimate judge of his ends, the belief that as far as possible his own views ought to govern his actions, that forms the essence of the individualist position.
This view does not, of course, exclude the recognition of social ends, or rather of a coincidence of individual ends which makes it advisable for men to combine for their pursuit. But it limits such common action to the instances where individual views coincide; what are called 'social ends' are for it merely identical ends of many individuals—or ends to the achievement of which individuals are willing to contribute in return for the assistance they receive in the satisfaction of their own desires. <strong>Common action is thus limited to the fields where people agree on common ends. Very frequently these common ends will not be ultimate ends to the individuals but means which different persons can use for different purposes.</strong> In fact, people are most likely to agree on common action where the common end is not an ultimate end to them but a means capable of serving a great variety of purposes."</em></p>

<p>[Friedrich A. von Hayek – The Road to Serfdom (1944), 59f.]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Freier" Wettbewerb + Sozialismus = Korporatismus]]></title>
    <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/05/06/freier-wettbewerb-sozialismus-korporatismus/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-06T05:19:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/05/06/freier-wettbewerb-sozialismus-korporatismus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"[...] <em>the universal struggle against competition promises to produce in the first instance something in many respects even worse, a state of affairs which can satisfy neither planners nor liberals; <a href="http://www.lewrockwell.com/paul/paul665.html">a sort of syndicalist or 'corporative' organization of industry</a>, in which competition is more or less suppressed but planning is left in the hands of the independent monopolies of the separate industries. This is the inevitable first result of a situation in which the people are united in their hostility to competition but agree on little else.<strong> By destroying competition in industry after industry, this policy puts the consumer at the mercy of the <a href="http://alles-schallundrauch.blogspot.com/2011/10/der-korporatismus-ist-unser-feind.html">joint monopolist action of capitalists</a></strong> and workers in the best organized industries. Yet, although this is a state of affairs which in wide fields has already existed for some time and although much of the muddled (and most of the interested) agitation for planning aims at it, it is not a state which is likely to persist or can be rationally justified. Such independent planning by industrial monopolies would, in fact, produce effects opposite to those at which the argument for planning aims. Once this stage is reached, the only alternative to return to competition is the control of the monopolies by the state—a control which, if it is to be made effective, must become progressively more complete and more detailed. It is this stage we are rapidly approaching. </em>[...]
<em>If we are, nevertheless, rapidly moving toward such a state,</em>{img right http://necedemalis.github.com/images/korporatismus.jpg 194 228 Korporatismus %}<em> this is largely because most people still belive that it is must be possible <a href="http://www.handelsblatt.com/politik/deutschland/wagenknechts-neues-buch-sozialismus-aber-bitte-liberal/4374552.html">to find some middle way</a> between 'atomistic' competition and central direction. Nothing, indeed, seems at first more plausible, or is more likely to appeal to reasonable people </em>[...]<em> Yet mere common sense proves a treacherous guide in this field. Although competition can bear some admixture of regulation, it cannot be combined with planning to any extent we like without ceasing to operate on an effective guide to production. Nor is 'planning' a medicine which, taken in small doses, can produce the effects for which one might hope from it thoroughgoing application. <strong>Both competition and central direction become poor and inefficient tools if they are incomplete.</strong>"</em></p>

<p>[Friedrich A. Hayek – The Road to Serfdom, 1944, S.40ff.]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wirtschaftliche Vereinigung – ohne politische Union]]></title>
    <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/05/05/wirtschaftliche-vereinigung-ohne-politische-union/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-05T02:01:26+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/05/05/wirtschaftliche-vereinigung-ohne-politische-union</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>"Wir sehen also, daß es weder nach wirtschaftlicher Erfahrung noch in wirtschaftlicher Theorie angezeigt ist, daß große, vereinte, territoriale Einheiten zu einer gesunden Entwicklung notwendig sind. Wenn die produktivste Form von Betrieben in fast allen Gebieten die kleine Einheit ist, dann ist kein Grund vorhanden, es mit einem gigantischen einheitlichen Hinterland zu umgeben. </em>[...]<em>
All das deutet darauf hin, daß die Wirtschaft, die das Hauptargument für die Vereinigung der Menschheit in Großraumordnungen, ja sogar in einen Weltstaat liefern sollte, tatsächlich mit dem <a href="https://mises.org/daily/2610">Grenznutzengesetz</a> das Argument für Kleinzellenstaaten liefert. </em>[...]<em>
Die Aufgabe der heutigen großen Einheitssysteme der großen Mächte aber würde nicht notwendigerweise die Zerstörung aller wirtschaftlichen Einheiten bedeuten, genauso, wie die Aufgabe einer zentralisierten Diktatur zugunsten einer 'individuellen' Selbstbestimmung nicht die Zerstörung aller früheren 'sozialen' Bande bedeutet. In anderen Worten bedeutet politischer Partikularismus nicht automatisch wirtschaftlicher Partikularismus, wie wir sehr gut in den Vereinigten Staaten sehen können oder in der wirtschaftlichen Zusammenarbeit der sonst ganz unabhängigen Benelux-Staaten. Er beinhaltet keinesfalls die Neuerrichtung irgendwelcher 'künstlicher' wirtschaftlicher Hindernisse, wie Zölle, Verkehrsbarrieren entlang der politischen Grenzen kleiner Staaten.
Es ist dieser Alptraum der Wiedereinführung von Grenzen, der <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=GK7vyL3pseA">die Einheitstheoretiker so bedrückt</a>, aber nur, weil sie sich nicht vorstellen können, daß Grenzen nicht notwendigerweise Barrieren bedeuten und daß sie ohne den Beigeschmack einer Barriere die Quelle unseres Glücks und nicht unseres Unglücks sind. Deshalb treiben uns unsere Instinkte immer danach, Grenzen zu errichten, nicht aber, sie niederzureißen. Wir ziehen sie um unsere Gärten als Zäune und in unseren Häusern in Form von Wänden, die unsere Zimmer trennen. </em>[...]<em>
Es sind Barrieren also, die sich in der Entwicklung der Menschheit <img class="right" src="http://necedemalis.github.com/images/Grenzen.jpeg" width="162" height="136" title="Kenne deine Grenzen" > unheilvoll auswirken, nicht die schützenden Grenzen, deren Funktion es ist, die Dinge in gesunden Bahnen zu halten. Und Barrieren, die man als <a href="http://blog.mises.org/7889/free-trade-versus-free-trade-agreements/">unnatürliche Grenzen</a> bezeichnen könnte, würden paradoxerweise sinnlos werden in einem idealen Staat eines konkurrenzierenden Kapitalismus, wo jede Geschäftseinheit ihre eigenen Grenzen zieht, bis sie auf die Kräfte der Konkurrenz trifft. Das ideale Bild einer Kleinstaatenwelt wäre demnach ein Ort der frei atmenden, wechselnden, selbstkontrollierten Grenzen, aber frei von allen unnatürlichen Hindernissen, wie Zoll- und Verkehrsbarrieren.
Überraschenderweise wäre das Resultat eines wirtschaftlichen Kleinzellensystems der Zerfall der <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wj_lmesvZOo&amp;feature=plcp">echten wirtschaftlichen Hindernisse</a>: Denn die Verkehrs- und die Handelsbarrieren würden ihren Sinn verlieren, ohne zur gleichen Zeit die politischen oder andere natürliche Grenzen zu zerstören. Die neue Wirtschaftskarte von Europa zum Beispiel würde überhaupt keine Grenzen zeigen. </em>[...]<em><strong> So gelangen wir zu einer besonderen Einheit, die akzeptabel ist, da sie keine machtaufbauenden Organisationsformen beinhaltet, mit all deren Gefahren, sondern eine physische Einheit mehrerer aneinandergrenzender Gebiete und Marktflecken darstellt. Hier hat Einheit Sinn.</strong> Erstens existiert sie, mit und ohne Grenzen. Zweitens, da sie eine Realität ist, muß sie versorgt werden, und so entsteht fast automatisch ein eigenes Versorgungssystem, über alle vom Menschen erfundenen Grenzen hinweg."</em></p>

<p>[Leopold Kohr – Das Ende der Großen (1957), 240ff.]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Masterplaner]]></title>
    <link href="http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/05/04/masterplaner/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T02:06:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://necedemalis.github.io/blog/2012/05/04/masterplaner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>"Darum kann kein Maß menschlicher Kontrolle, ob von Karl Marx oder <a href="http://www.wirtschaftslexikon24.net/d/deficit-spending/deficit-spending.htm">Lord Keynes</a> vorgeschlagen, eine Lösung für Probleme darstellen, welche gerade darum angestiegen sind, weil ein Organismus jeglicher menschlichen Kontrolle entwachsen ist. Die Probleme der <a href="http://www.economicsjunkie.com/the-business-cycle">modernen Wirtschaftszyklen</a> haben ihre Ursachen weder im 'natürlichen' Funktionieren des Kapitalismus noch in den schlecht verwalteten oder unausgereiften Funktionen des Kommunismus. Die Ursache liegt in der <a href="http://ef-magazin.de/2011/12/06/3305-eurozone-wie-soll-eine-fiskalunion-funktionieren">Überdimensioniertheit der modernen Wirtschaftssysteme</a>. </em>[...]<em> Und diese Gigantomanie ist die natürliche Begleiterscheinung nicht nur des Kapitalismus, sondern jeder überdimensionierten Entwicklung.
<strong>Die Idee, daß zyklische Schwankungen, insoweit sie ein Hauptproblem ausmachen, Größenphänomene sind und nicht Phänomene des Kapitalismus</strong>, scheint auch von der Tatsache bestätigt zu sein, daß zur Zeit, als sie im kommunistischen Rußland, welches groß ist, auftraten, ihre zerstörerische Natur in kapitalistischen Ländern, die sowohl politisch als auch wirtschaftlich kleingeblieben sind, ausblieben."</em></p>

<p>[Leopold Kohr – Das Ende der Großen (1957), S.222]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
